<sect2><title>OracleAccess Semantics</title>
<sect3><title>The logical data hiererchy</title>
<para>In order to connect to an Oracle database using CORAL one should
specify a  connection string which typically has a format such as
<programlisting>
oracle://databaseServerName:port/schemaName/serviceName
</programlisting>
where the port number is optional.
</para>
<para>
The schema name is in practice the user name of an oracle user.
A user has access to the tables defined in the schema of another user
for which all the relevant privileges have been granted.
</para>
<para>The database server name refers either to the logical name which should appear
as an entry in the $(TNS_ADMIN)/tnsnames.ora file, or an actual server
hosting the database.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Controlling Oracle-specific parameters</title>
<sect4><title>Table spaces</title>
<para>New tables, indices and LOBs are created in the default table space of
the user. This may not always be the optimum behaviour for a user who
may wish that indices especially are created in different table
spaces. There are three ways which allow the user specify the table
space for new tables and indices:
<orderedlist>
<listitem><para>By setting the environment variables
<emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_TS_TAB</emphasis>,
<emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_TS_IND</emphasis> and
<emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_TS_LOB</emphasis> to the name of the
table space for new tables, indices and LOBs respectively.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>By setting the properties
<emphasis role="bold">TableSpaceForTables</emphasis>,
<emphasis role="bold">TableSpaceForIndices</emphasis> and
<emphasis role="bold">TableSpaceForLobs</emphasis> of the
IRelationalDomain component "CORAL/RelationalPlugins/oracle" to the
name of the table space for new tables, indices and LOBsrespectively.</para></listitem>
<listitem>By overriding the default values (empty string) in the
relevant methods of the CORAL API with the actual ones. </listitem>
</orderedlist>
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>LOB handling</title>
<para>
When reading back a LOB object from the database, this is done in
chunks which have a default size of 1024 bytes (1 KB). This default
value can changed by setting the property <emphasis role="bold">LobChunkSize</emphasis>
or the environment variable <emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_LOB_CHUNK_SIZE</emphasis>
accordingly.
</para>
</sect4>

<sect4><title>Enabling SQL TRACE</title>
<para>
A user can trigger the generation of a trace file in the database
server, whenever he/she authenticates, by setting the environment variable
<emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_SQL_TRACE_ON</emphasis> to any value.
</para>
<para>In case the environment variable <emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_CERN_TRACE_ON</emphasis>
is set, it takes precedence over CORAL_ORA_SQL_TRACE_ON and executes
the CERN_TRACE package in the server, which has to be already
installed on the server by the system administrators. This also
triggers the generation of the trace file, and whenever the user
session is ended the trace file is sent by mail to the address stored
in the environment variable CORAL_ORA_CERN_TRACE_ON.
</para>
</sect4>

</sect3>

</sect2>
