<sect2><title>LFCReplicaService Semantics</title>
<sect3><title>Architecture</title>
<para>
The LFCReplicaService is a database replica catalogue using an LFC
server as a storage backend. 
The translation of the LFC stored data to the database-related
information is implemented in the client-side code, based on the LFC
C-API client.
Each database replica is stored with its associated information,
including the authentication credential (pair username+password),
database server host name, status of the server.
In order to protect the access to the replica entry for the disclosure
of the associated authentication credentials, the
LFCReplicaService fully uses the LFC built-in security scheme
permission. 
The LFC uses
the Grid (proxy) certificates extended with the VOMS information to
establish the identity of the client, and regulates the access to the
file entries with a file-system like access permission scheme, which
includes ACL's. 
In order to adopt this security scheme, the
LFCReplicaService defines a database catalogue entry (=a logical file
name on the LFC side) for each role to be coupled to a credential
pair.In such a way the role entry, represented by an entry in the
LFC file system, can be protected for the access using the standard
LFC security scheme, allowing only the intended grid roles or groups
to access the file and disclose the authentication credentials.  
</para>
</sect3>
<sect3><title>LFC Server Connection</title>
<para>
The LFC C-API client does not allow an explicit connection with a
given LFC server. The connection is established implicitly, at any
function call accessing the LFC name server. The LFC host is specified
with the environment variable LFC_HOST.
In order to be authenticated into a secure LFC name server, the user
needs a valid grid certificate to be available in the execution
context.
In case of missing valid certificate, the LFC will return the error message: 
"send2nsd: NS002 - send error : No valid credential found".
</para>
</sect3>
<sect3><title>Deployment of CORAL database catalogue into an existing
LFC server</title>
<para>
In order to use an existing LFC server as a database catalogue, very
little deployment operation is required. Since the operation of the
database entries involves the management of the database
authentication credentials, it is assumed that it will be performed by
a super-user, acting as
database catalogue administrator. 
The first action required is the definition of the database catalogue
area in the LFC file system. By default, the LFCReplicaService assumes
the folder /database as a root base folder for the database entries.
Optionally, a user defined folder can be assumed as root, by setting
the environment variable CORAL_LFC_BASEDIR.
In both cases, the corrisponding folder has to be created and set with
the necessary access permission RWX to the db catalogue administrator.
In order to add a replica set, the administrator will run the
coral_replica_manager -add command, specifying all the required
parameters.
The entry created will be by default not accessible to the world.
In order to let a specific grid identity (role or group) access the
database entry, the db administrator has to run the
coral_replica_manager -set_perm command for all the group entitled to
access the replicas.
</para>
<para>
Example:
</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
logical connection name:  /atlas/ecal/calib
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
physical connection string: oracle://ecal_calib/calib_writer
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
username:          calib_reader
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
password:          xyz2006
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
database server:   atlr
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
coral role:        writer
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
to be visible for grid role: offline_reader
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para> the commands necessary:</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
coral_replica_manager -add -l /atlas/ecal/calib -c oracle://ecal_calib/calib_writer 
                           -r writer -u calib_reader -p xyz2006 
</programlisting>
</para>
<para>
<programlisting>
coral_replica_manager -set_perm -l /atlas/ecal/calib -r writer -g offline_writer -ro
</programlisting>
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3><title>Storage of database password in the LFC server</title>
<para>
In order to avoid storage of clear text password in the LFC tables, a
simple key-based mechansim of encryption has been implemented.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
