<!-- $Id: Semantics.xml,v 1.6 2007/01/25 12:31:30 ioannis Exp $ -->
<sect2> <title>FrontierAccess Semantics</title>
 <sect3> <title>The logical data hierarchy</title>
  <para>
   In order to connect to an Oracle database using Frontier one should
   specify a  connection string which typically used to have the format as
   <programlisting>
    frontier://FrontierServerName:port/serviceBaseURL/SCHEMA_NAME
   </programlisting>
   which gets translated automatically into valid Frontier URL in form:
   <programlisting>
    http://FrontierServerName:port/serviceBaseURL
   </programlisting>

   where the port number is optional but one has to pay attention to
   it as the same connection string can differ only in port number
   which may indicate that the server is cache instead of an
   application server.
  </para>
  <para>
   The schema name is in practice the user name of an oracle user.
   A user has access to the tables defined in the schema of another user
   for which all the relevant privileges have been granted. Frontier
   application server usually connects only via one acount, so when
   the tables are created in an Oracle database to which Frontier
   application server connects, then is required that the proper SELECT
   access rights on these tables are granted to the Frontier user,
   otherwise FrontierAccess will not work.
  </para>
  <para>
   The FrontierAccess now decodes and passes down to the underlying
   frontier_client library the new conneciton string format which may
   look like:
   <programlisting>
    frontier://(proxyurl=http://srv.fnal.gov:3128)(proxyurl=http://srv15.fnal.gov:3128)
               (serverurl=http://frontier.cern.ch:8000/Frontier)(serverurl=http://frontier1.cern.ch:8000/Frontier)
               (retrieve-ziplevel=5)
              /SCHEMA_NAME
   </programlisting>
   The complex connection string now contains all the parameters to
   let the frontier_client library to perform load-balancing and
   fail-over itself and configure the compression level used for data
   transfer.
  </para>
 </sect3>

 <sect3> <title>Controlling Frontier-specific parameters</title>
  <sect4> <title>Refreshing cache contents</title>
   <para>
    FrontierAccess is primarily going to access the cached
    information. There are, however, situations where it is not desired or a
    fresh information is needed. This typically happens when database
    schema has been updated. In order to make sure that FrontierAccess
    uses the most recent database objects it forces a cache to be
    refreshed for data dictionary queries.
    For the the data queries the cache access is enabled &amp;
    preferred.

    In cases where there is a need to refresh cache contents due to
    updates in the back-end databases one can control the refresh
    behavior by using coral::IWebCacheControl API. This
    interface allows to inform the FrontierAccess plug-in to execute
    its queries with refresh parameter enabled, thus causing the
    refresh of all the Squid caches on the way up to a Frontier
    server. 

    The access to the coral::IWebCacheControl interface is via
    coral::ConnectionService component. 
    Once the web cache control handle is obtained one can force
    reloading of a whole database schema, e.g. the queries involving
    any table in the given schema will be executed with refresh
    enabled or one can do finer selection by registering
    specific table names so the FrontierAccess plug-in enables
    refresh only for the queries which involve any of the registred
    tables.
   </para>
   <para>
    Imagine the following data source setup using CORAL data service
    lookup mechanism reading input from dblookup.xml file:

    <screen>
    <![CDATA[
    <?xml version="1.0" ?>
     <servicelist>
       <logicalservice name="/coral/CoolFrontier">
         <service name="frontier://afrontier.cern.ch:8080/Frontier/CORAL" accessMode="readonly" />
       </logicalservice>
     <servicelist>
    ]]>
    </screen>

    then the application code needs to do the following to switch on
    refresh for the all queries to schema CORAL as follows:

    <programlisting>
      // Locate the CORAL ConnectionService component
      seal::IHandle&lt;coral::IConnectionService&gt;
      connectionService = appcontext->query&lt;coral::IConnectionService&gt;( "CORAL/Services/ConnectionService" );
      // Setup refresh
      coral::IWebCacheControl&amp; webcache = connectionService-&gt;webCacheControl();
      // Set refresh for the whole schema, e.g. each query in this schema will skip Squid cache
      // NOTE! One must specify the physical connection string as the plugins don't know about the logical ones!!!
      webcache.refreshSchemaInfo( "http://atlasfrontier.cern.ch:8080/Frontier" );
    </programlisting>

    Please note the fact that one needs to specify the real physical
    connection string being actually used to connect to the Frontier
    server and with the "frontier://" prefix being already rewritten
    as "http://". The same applies for the new complex conneciton
    string syntax just the "http://" will not be there because is not
    needed anymore.

    One can select also the particular tables in the target schema to
    become subject to refresh for each query run against them. See the API
    of coral::IWebCacheControl interface.
   </para>
  </sect4>
  <sect4> <title>Enabling Frontier client debug log</title>
   <para>
    A user can trigger the more verbose log output, by setting the
    environment variable
    <emphasis role="bold">FRONTIER_LOG_LEVEL=Debug</emphasis>.
   </para>
  </sect4>
<!--
<sect4><title>LOB handling</title>
<para>
When reading back a LOB object from the database, this is done in
chunks which have a default size of 1024 bytes (1 KB). This default
value can changed by setting the property <emphasis role="bold">LobChunkSize</emphasis>
or the environment variable <emphasis role="bold">CORAL_ORA_LOB_CHUNK_SIZE</emphasis>
accordingly.
</para>
</sect4>
-->
 </sect3>
</sect2>
